[whimsical ethereal music playing]
[people chattering]
[Alejandra] I always dreamed
about being a mom.
I got married when I was 17
and full of hope.
I was pregnant which was partially
why we decided to get married.
But I've always loved Arturo.
I've always liked children.
I've always been drawn to them.
And all the kids in my family,
they…
They, mm, have always
been very attached to me though.
My family is pretty big.
My family has… well they,
all have children, you know?
All my cousins have children.
So I…
So I like the idea
of just me being a mom. Yeah, so, um…
It was like, like fulfilling my dream
of having a family.
Since I got pregnant and we got married,
that was always our plan.
I always, always saw myself as a mom.
[director] Cut. Great. I love it.
Can we try a version that's more fluid?
The text you're going to read
is from an interview we have to emulate,
and the character you would have to play
-is Ale, from 15 years ago.
-[actress] Mm.
-Like a flashback that the actress has…
-[actress] Yeah.
about the real Ale, okay?
[quiet dramatic music playing]
-[woman] Casting, 1F, take one.
-[man] Mark.
I wanted it so bad, you know?
And… I found myself
in all these complicated situations.
So I began to make
some choices
which caused things to start getting
even more complicated.
Until there was nowhere to go.
I was in over my head.
[whimsical ethereal music playing]
A CHILD OF MY OWN
[camera shutter clicks]
[photographer] Very good.
[camera whirring]
That's it.
-One more.
-[camera shutter clicks]
Great. Uh, can we get closer, please.
[music stops]
Great, perfect. Uh, look at the camera.
Perfect. Smile.
Let's see that joy for Ale and Arturo.
["Unchained Melody"
by The Righteous Brothers playing]
ALEJANDRA AND ARTURO
OUR WEDDING
[applause and cheering]
♪ I've hungered for your touch ♪
♪ A long, lonely time ♪
[crowd] Kiss! Kiss! Kiss! Kiss! Kiss!
[Alejandra] When I got married,
I think the biggest pressure I felt
was to make his family happy.
I was always really accepted
by my own family,
so being a part of his family
and not feeling accepted by his mother
made me feel like
I had to earn my place to feel accepted.
[all chanting]
Forever together,
always and forever! [cheering]
[machine clicks]
[clock ticking]
[moody dramatic music playing]
[Alejandra] I lost my baby
living with my in-laws.
I didn't want to see anyone.
But they came up to my room,
and one of Arturo’s aunts asked me…
-Why are you crying? Don't cry.
-[Alejandra] "Why are you crying?"
-"We've all been there before."
-Yes, it's terrible.
[Alejandra] His mom said,
"It's because you're not careful."
Grandma!
How are you feeling, Ale?
[Alejandra] I had to lie there,
listening to everything they were saying
until my mom got there.
I’m here, honey.
[kissing]
Why did I miscarry?
[moody dramatic music continues]
-[Alejandra] It was my fault.
-It was all my fault.
[Alejandra] Because I didn't take care
of myself. Because I ran, I went to work.
-I blamed myself for everything.
-No, it wasn't your fault, relax.
Get some rest, okay?
[whimpers faintly]
[people chuckle]
Hey, so we're gonna have
a big yard for a party, huh?
-Cheers!
-[people] Cheers.
[woman 1] So the house
is really big then? Congrats.
[woman 2] That's super exciting.
-Maybe you'll come over soon.
-[woman 3] Can't wait to see it.
[overlapping chatter]
The house is very nice,
but it's big for them.
-They don't even have children.
-Ma.
-Or maybe they'll fill it with dogs?
-[man 2] Mom, stop.
-Lot of dogs here.
-[man 3] All those rooms,
-you've gotta fill 'em with something.
[man 2] You too, Uncle?
[woman 2] We just want you both
to be happy there.
It would be so nice
to have a few running around there.
[woman 4] I want
to meet a great-grandchild of mine.
Well, yeah, Grandma, but I'm only 25.
Well, you had better
start soon then, dear.
[woman 2] Otherwise, they'll look like
your grandkids instead of your children.
[Arturo's uncle] Why don't you adopt?
No, it's not the same, right?
We're gonna have kids of our own.
And Ale has been very busy
working at the hospital, it's demanding.
-But we're on it.
-[Arturo's mother] Those are priorities.
-Don't wait too long.
-[Arturo's uncle] Thank you.
-Erik, Another one?
-[Erik] No, thanks.
-Bring me two cold ones, please?
-Yeah.
[quiet ethereal music playing]
[typing]
-[man] What happened after that loss?
-I got pregnant again soon after, right?
Arturo was always telling me, "Careful,
Ale. Don’t do this, don’t do that."
Yeah, we fought the last time
about the pregnancy.
I told her she had to be careful,
had to rest.
I work all day, I can't be following
her around, reminding her.
I even said, "Do it for the baby,
if you can't do it for yourself."
but she's stubborn like that.
I mean it.
And well, I lost that pregnancy.
That was my second time
having a miscarriage.
After a few years
we started to worry, right?
We realized a baby wasn't coming.
Doctor, this is very hard for me, because
I want to have a child and I can't.
We don't know what the problem is.
It happened once naturally,
so why won't it happen again?
We're not using any protection, so…
I don't know. I think there's something
wrong in her body that can't keep it like…
I don't know.
[doctor] Don't worry.
We're going to see how your uterus
is doing after the curettage,
and we're also going to analyze
your husband’s semen.
We could even try doing
artificial insemination
to help you get pregnant.
That prevents loses, right?
No pregnancy is guaranteed
to succeed 100%.
But nature is wise, and it won’t allow
an unhealthy baby to reach full term.
You are both very young.
You still have time.
[exhales deeply]
[Alejandra's mother] Okay, okay, okay,
almost there, almost there.
You'll be all right.
Thanks.
[moody dramatic music playing]
[whimsical ethereal music playing]
[Alejandra] When I finally got pregnant
the third time, Arturo said,
"Now you have to take care of yourself."
"Now you have to do this,
now you have to do that."
"Now you need to stay here."
"Actually, you have to stop working."
And I was like, "No, what are you talking
about? I'm not going to stop working."
And he would say, "You are so stubborn."
-Hi, Ale.
-Hi, doctor.
How are you feeling?
Great. I'm not nauseous anymore.
-Is everything ready?
-Uh-huh.
Hello. Good morning. Come in.
-Thank you. We'll have coffee now, okay?
-Okay.
[moody music playing]
[Alejandra] I showed up
at my boss's office crying
and said, "I don't feel well."
Ale, I'm so sorry,
but with the bleeding… the baby's gone.
Oh no, not again.
I'm sorry.
How am I going to tell Arturo, doctor?
Try to relax, hm?
Relax and
talk to your husband,
discuss your options.
It's going to be very difficult for you
to have a pregnancy reach full-term.
I'll let you get dressed.
[Alejandra] Afterwards,
I sat in the clinic waiting room
with mixed feelings.
I blamed myself, obviously.
[moody music stops]
Look, can someone please help me?
I've been waiting here for hours.
[receptionist] You have to wait your turn.
You can't do anything?
[Alejandra] You ask God, "Why me?"
"Why is this happening? Why?"
That’s when I met Mayra.
[whimpering quietly]
What's wrong?
I want to be a mom, and I can’t.
I'm going to be a mom, and don't want to.
[quiet dramatic music playing]
What?
I just found out.
[Alejandra] Mayra tells me…
-I don't want to have it.
-[Alejandra] …she wanted an abortion.
The dad doesn't want
to take responsibility
because he says it's not his.
And I… I can’t have another baby.
But, but you can have it by yourself.
No.
I don't study or work.
I just help my mom with stuff.
[actress] You can get a job.
Sell something, I don't know.
No, no, no, working isn't for me.
I do sell some stuff, but no.
No. I can’t have another baby.
I already have a daughter. If I have
another baby, my mom will kill me.
She'll kick me out of the house
and go crazy.
She wouldn't be able to kick you out.
Yeah, she will.
Oh, man.
I'd rather give it away
than get rid of it.
I guess.
[Alejandra] Then, she says, "I'd rather
give it away than get rid of it."
What?
I wanna give it away.
[gentle upbeat music playing]
Are you serious?
Yes.
[Alejandra] And at the time,
you think it's God,
fate, the universe…
If you’re sure, I can keep your baby.
[Alejandra] …that puts people
in your path,
and maybe God wants you
to do something, right?
[Mayra] Yes.
I swear, I'll take care
of everything for your baby.
I promise you.
My name's Mayra.
[actress]
Nice to meet you. I'm Ale.
[sighs]
Look.
OBGYN ADMIN SUPPORT
I work in Gynecology.
Yes, I noticed.
I guess we can start your paperwork
so you can have your appointments here.
Okay.
PERSONAL INFORMATION
[Alejandra] Deep down, I was worried
that she would try to blackmail me,
so the less information
she had about me, the better.
So I said, "I'll see you here.
I work in Women's Health."
"Don't worry.
Whatever you need, I'll be here."
This lets you have
all your appointments here.
And I also made
your ultrasound appointment.
-We'll see you April 20th.
-Yeah.
-At eight.
-Mm-hm.
[mysterious music playing]
[moody dramatic music playing]
[Alejandra] I went home,
and when I got there I thought,
"I'm not gonna tell anyone."
Mostly, I wasn't telling Arturo.
Why? Because I didn’t want to be blamed.
I didn't want to hear,
yet again, "I told you so,"
or "It's your fault,"
or, "You don't understand."
[moody dramatic music fades]
4 MONTHS PREGNANT: YOUR BODY TRANSFORMS
PHYSICAL AND HORMONAL CHANGES
[whispering] Shut the baby…
[lively classical music playing]
THE POWER OF PREGNANCY
FOODS THAT CAUSE WEIGHT GAIN
[music stops]
-You say no. Doesn't make sense.
-What's the problem?
What were you doing? We couldn't find you.
-I was at school.
-He says he was at school.
-That's what he says.
-Here you are.
Mom always has my back.
[Arturo’s mother]
This pozole looks really good.
Hey, damn, I want what you're having.
Well, this is my pregnant diet
by my doctor, okay?
[Erik] Well, introduce me
to that doctor, please.
-Hey, respect my wife. Mom, look at him.
-[Erik chuckles]
-[Arturo's mother] How are you feeling?
-Fine.
[Arturo's mother] You can't tell from
your eyes. Her eyes don't look sunken.
-[Arturo] Mom, stop.
-I think that's an old wives' tales.
Stop. Hey.
Hey, sweetie,
I bought you some ground beef. Come here.
Peppers, to make stuffed peppers
and some eggs.
-And people say I don't spoil him.
-[Erik] Oh, yeah.
Would you look,
I even iron his clothes, and I'm pregnant.
Well, pregnancy isn't a malady,
my dear. You can do anything.
No, Mom, she can't do anything.
She's already had two miscarriages.
She has to be careful.
[Arturo's mother]
Well, I'm from a different time.
[Arturo] You okay? What’s wrong?
She's still having a lot of nausea
from the pregnancy.
She'll be right back.
-Do you like it? Not eating much.
-[Arturo's mother] Mm-hm.
[mysterious music playing]
[Alejandra] So far,
everything was going as planned.
Arturo believed me.
He really thought that I was pregnant.
-How far along are you?
-Five months.
Ale, why did you change jobs?
Yeah, I mean,
Urology is much more demanding.
Besides, all pregnant women are treated
in Gynecology with Dr. Guerrero.
-It’s easier if you're working there.
-No, I've been needing a new job.
Gynecology is too much.
[nurse 1] But, Ale,
you're five months pregnant.
You should have stayed there
doing paperwork, sitting at your desk.
No, it seems like normal hours,
eight to three,
but no, you always have to do extra.
[nurse 2] Hm.
Every night,
it was really stressful for me to stay.
All the time, Arturo keeps saying,
"Hey, Alejandra,
you can't keep doing this."
"You get home so late."
[nurse 2] Yeah, I get it.
A man need his wife, right?
[chuckles]
[nurse 1] Well, my sister's husband
left her basically overnight
for far less than that.
-Oh my God, heaven forbid.
-[nurse 2] Are you serious? No.
Imagine him leaving now.
[nurse 2 chuckles]
No, no, no.
No. But that's why I behave.
I mean, we're happier like this.
[nurse 2 chuckles]
Well, I hope it's what's best
for you three of you.
-Do you want some water?
-Yes, please.
[quiet ethereal music playing]
THE POWER OF PREGNANCY
[Alejandra] When I started gaining weight,
everything began to change.
Absolutely everything, my body,
having to buy maternity clothes.
With all the weight I was gaining,
my stomach really looked
like a pregnancy bump,
So, when Arturo and I were intimate,
whenever I felt his hand on my stomach,
I instinctively tightened my muscles
so it felt more firm.
Arturo. Arturo. Arturo, no.
-I know, but I want to.
-I can’t.
-The doctor told me not right now.
-But why not? Come on.
-I can't do it. I can't do this right now.
-Why?
-I'm telling you, no.
-[sighs]
It can be dangerous.
-It could cause a premature baby birth.
-[sighs]
What if we hit its head
and he comes early?
He said it was called something like
total occlusion placenta previa.
Your stomach is hard but it looks small.
The baby's small
and that's the problem, you know?
When are you having
another checkup at the hospital?
I don't know.
The other day,
your mom wanted to see an ultrasound.
They already did it
and everything was good.
And the others, the other ultrasounds,
when did you do them?
About a month ago.
I don't have the copies yet.
I mean, Arturo,
I do all of it at the hospital,
but I didn't get anything.
Mm. And nowhere else
is going to do better.
Yeah?
Well, all right then.
If you're happy, I'm happy.
[Alejandra] I slept next to him,
I had lived with him.
If he said something, I’d immediately say,
"You're bothering me."
-"You’re hurting me."
-[Arturo sighs]
"Don't you know that hurts?"
I guess it was the same kind of emotional
blackmail I always used on him.
-How are you?
-Fine
Hmm. Did you get the ultrasound?
Yes, but they had me waiting for hours.
Haven't eaten anything.
Let's see.
Have some.
I also brought your vitamins.
Take them, okay?
Did they say anything?
It's a girl, and she's underweight.
Hey, you're getting fat.
Are you sure you're not pregnant?
Oh no, I wish. Mmm.
What do you mean?
Is there a due date?
[Mayra] Mm-hm.
They think I'll give birth
the week of June 16th.
I have to go. I've been here all morning.
[zipper zips]
Okay.
You're not alone. I'm always here. Hm?
[kiss]
-See you in two months.
-Yeah.
I'll see you on June 16th.
ULTRASOUND
[quiet ethereal music playing]
[typing]
[actress] Let me introduce
our new family member.
They finally gave it to you?
See, my love? That's the advantage
of not leaving the hospital.
You both have no idea
how hard it was to get them.
-I explained that it was important to me.
-How are you, little guy.
Hello, baby Arturo.
He's Arturo junior, yeah?
-Why does that matter?
-What do you mean?
Because maybe it's a girl!
It doesn't look like a girl
from how you're carrying.
-That's what the doctors said.
-You're not a girl.
Don't worry, Arturo, it's not a girl.
-I think that they'd know. [chuckles]
-You hear that?
-Either way, it'll be God's will. Right?
-Yeah. It's God's will.
-Yeah.
-Daddy loves you, little Arturo.
-Need anything?
-[actress] Yes.
Tea, please.
"They're going to have a house full
of dogs. I won't get to have grandkids."
I'll fill the house
with dogs that bite you,
-dumb mother-in-law. [groans]
-Hey. Go easy, that's my mother.
She loves you very much.
She asks about you.
She's very happy that you're pregnant.
-Yeah, I can tell.
-[scoffs]
Look at this one. It's so cute.
Yeah, it's cute.
I think maybe one that's a little longer,
yeah, at the bottom?
My love.
One of my friends bought this
for her baby.
She's adopting him.
Yeah, her mom didn't want him
and can't take care of him.
So, well, she's going to keep him.
-Arturo, I’m talking to you.
-So, I’m listening.
You're not paying attention though.
What do you want me to say? "It's fine"?
She should try her best,
even if the kid isn't hers.
But the kid is hers, yeah?
If she raises it, it's hers.
Yeah, but it's not the same.
I could never adopt a baby.
-Okay, but why?
-Just because.
It's not the same.
I don't want to hurt the kid, you know?
What if I can't love him like I should?
[groans] Ale.
-Why are you getting upset?
-Mm.
Calm down. Don't let the baby hear.
If it’s a boy, he'll look like you.
If it’s a girl, she'll look like me.
Mm. As long as my girl's
not like your mom, all right?
Hey, that's my mom.
[ethereal music playing]
[Alejandra] I felt very special.
From the minute the people who love you
start treating you
with that kind of affection,
filled with anticipation
and with, with hope,
where they see you and touch your belly
and, and they treat you so nicely…
-Everything's so pretty.
-Thank you.
-You look pretty too, Ale.
-[laughter]
Okay, that one's done.
So exciting! Are you excited?
Oh, yeah.
[woman 1] The prettiest aunt around.
Look at that. Here I am.
[woman 1] What would you name the baby?
NAME OPTIONS
-If it's a girl, Alejandra.
-[woman 1] Uh-huh. Okay.
If it’s a boy,
I’d like him to be called Arturo.
-[woman 1] There already two Arturos.
-After their dad and mom.
-Aww, look how pretty.
-[woman 1 laughs]
-Yes, there's that and here are the girls.
-[woman 2] "Alejandra's baby shower."
-[woman 1] Say hi!
-[woman 3] Mom of the year.
[woman 1] We love it. What do we say?
Let's do this!
[women] Mom of the year!
Mom of the year!
Mom of the year! Mom of the year!
[woman 1] Ale, smile!
All right, it’s okay. What are we missing?
Let’s see. Anything else?
Let's all clap for the baby!
Give me an A, an L and an E!
Put it all together now
and what does that spell?
Ale! Ale! Rah! Rah! Rah!
[woman] Congratulations!
[entertainer] You have only one month left
before your baby's born.
Do you have anything
you want to say to your guests?
-[women] Ale! Ale! Ale! Ale! Ale!
-Yes. Boy. Well…
[Alejandra] I feel like I was living
in, in another dimension. I don’t know.
Well, uh, um…
Firstly, I want to thank you all
for being here.
And, um, I
just wanna say…
[shuddering]
-…I couldn't be… uh, uh…
-[quiet dramatic music playing]
…more grateful, yeah,
having you here celebrating with me.
[Alejandra] There were so any times
I just wanted to say,
"It's not real.
This isn't happening." But I couldn't.
-[entertainer] Anyone else? The grandmas?
-Me! Me! I want to say something.
I mean, I just…
I want to thank you all
for coming to celebrate with me and Ale.
Because this baby has been
long-awaited by this family.
I hope everything goes well, my dear.
This baby will be cute.
-Hmm?
-[women] Bravo!
Okay, everybody, let's eat.
Come on, there's so much to eat.
Come on. Let me serve you.
[Alejandra] I was really suffering.
I mean, I pretended like I was fine,
but I was suffering on the inside.
I mean, it hurt to see
how happy my parents were,
my family, my grandmother.
[no audible dialogue]
I wish someone
had burst that bubble of lies
and made everything come out.
I wish right there and then
someone would've said, "Wake up!"
[quiet dramatic music fades]
-[Alejandra's mother] Like that one?
-[actress] Yes.
-That's with the discount, right?
-Yes, 20% off.
Arturo, this one.
Did you see this one? It’s the same.
It's not the same. I like this one.
[Arturo] Aren't you getting ahead of
yourself with color? What if it's a boy?
Well, do you have to like it,
or maybe it's me.
-[Arturo] Mm.
-[actress] I like this one.
All right, it's fine.
We’ll take this one, pretty please.
Thanks.
I want to sit down.
[Alejandra] I was so, so fat.
I mean, literally weighed 98 kilos.
I had gained way too much weight.
I didn't feel good. Everything hurt.
I get tired when I stand up too long.
[Alejandra] And Arturo was thinking,
"Something's not right."
-It's okay, my love.
-[Alejandra] "Something’s wrong."
-Time for maternity leave.
-No, I won't stop, I can't stop.
You know me, I can keep working there, so…
Ale, why won't you just go on leave?
It's good for the baby.
Okay, yeah, you're right, okay.
-But just leave me alone.
-I’ll go with you, okay?
No, Arturo, you don't have to go with me.
No way. You're taking me.
-It's not necessary.
-You're taking me with you.
LAB ORDER - PATIENT NAME:
MARÍN MENDOZA, ELEONOR ALEJANDRA
[Alejandra] I couldn't keep
excluding Arturo.
Since I worked for so long
at the hospital,
well, I learned how to do a few things
and had some clinical knowledge.
So, I created my own medical records.
MEDICAL RECORD
12 WEEKS - 14 WEEKS - 17 WEEKS
20 WEEKS - 22 WEEKS - 27 WEEKS
[intriguing music playing]
When we went
to request my maternity leave,
I was thinking,
"How do I get out of here?"
"What's my escape route
when they find out that I'm not pregnant?"
-"They’ll say I'm crazy, insane."
-[doctor] How far along are you?
Uh, ma'am?
How far along are you?
Uh, 38 weeks, so--
[doctor] Good. And how do you feel?
Fine.
[doctor] Any pain, dizziness,
nausea? Trouble sleeping?
No, nothing.
[doctor] Good. I'm going to place a device
to listen to the baby’s heartbeat.
Okay?
[intriguing music continues faintly]
[distortion noise]
[audio rumbling]
No. I can't hear it.
You can't hear anything?
[doctor] I think it’s the device.
The old ones were better.
I'll get another one.
I told you we should have come in sooner.
[actress]
Arturo, I wanted to come sooner.
[Arturo groans]
Arturo. Arturo.
[Arturo] What?
-It’s just--
-[Arturo] It's just what?
I just…
[door closes]
Let's see.
If I may.
There it is.
[music becomes quiet and suspenseful]
Good.
-[Arturo] So, doctor…
-[exhales deeply]
…everything's fine with my baby, right?
Yes, yes.
I'll grant you your maternity leave.
[Alejandra] The doctor gave me
90 days of maternity leave,
so Arturo was relieved.
I was, I mean, really, at that point,
-I wasn't Alejandra anymore.
-[exhales deeply]
I mean, Alejandra, at that point,
was a mixture of everything.
I was sick, I mean, I was not well.
[lively classical music playing]
[camera shutter clicks]
In my head I was saying,
"What if I actually am pregnant?"
"What if I didn't have a miscarriage
or maybe I got pregnant again?"
"If I'm pregnant, how am I gonna do this?"
There was a lot going on in my head
that wasn't right.
[woman] Well done!
Okay, now we'll do it one more time.
[music fades]
-Going out?
-To the hospital.
Why are you going to work, babe?
Thought you were on leave.
You don't have to go.
You're giving birth soon. It'll end badly.
It's good for me to go. It's distracting.
And besides, my quarterly report is today.
I have to help my colleagues.
-And what am I gonna do here?
-You'll rest. You need to rest.
I can't let them fly solo.
I have to help them.
-They don't know how to do it.
-So what if they can't.
-You need to be careful.
-No, I can't miss it.
And like your mom says,
"Pregnancy is not a malady," hm?
Fine then.
But don't hurt my baby, okay?
BIRTH LOG
HOSPITAL RECORDS
PATIENT NAME - TYPE OF BIRTH
[suspenseful music playing]
Hi, my love.
-Ah!
-Hi, Ale! How've you been?
-Oh my God, great, and you?
-Good.
Can you check on my neighbor?
She should be in now.
Sure. Let's see, what's her name?
[actress]
Her name is Mayra Navarro Vega.
Mayra?
-Mm-hm. My neighbor told me she was due.
-[nurse] Let's see.
Mayra, Mayra…
Let’s see. Let's see. Yes, here she is.
She came today, but they scheduled her
for a C-section tomorrow.
[music fades]
-[Arturo] Let's make a video for the baby.
-No.
-Come on.
-I'm too tired.
The baby could come tomorrow.
No, tomorrow they’ll tell me
if they're going to induce labor.
-Fine.
-Hey.
-Huh?
-I'm craving chocolate. Can you get it?
Yeah, just a minute.
You ready?
-Our baby's coming tomorrow.
-Mm-hm.
[Arturo] Aren't you excited?
So much I can't even show it.
[Arturo] Let's see that big belly.
When they see this video
in about ten years,
they'll see how big your belly was.
My baby is in there.
My son! [chuckles]
Everyone's gonna come see him.
He’s gonna live here with us
in this home.
The one we bought, just for him.
Right?
[quite mystical music playing]
PEOPLE IN RECOVERY ROOMS
MAYRA A. NAVARRO V.
CESAREAN SECTION
[distant babies crying]
[music fades]
[cell phone vibrating]
ARTURO
CALL REJECTED
Ale, how are you?
Hi, sweetie.
-What are you doing here?
-I came to see my neighbor, yeah?
-I'll find you in a bit, okay?
-Yes!
[Alejandra] I went upstairs
to see Mayra around 12:30
when they took her to her room.
[quiet dramatic music playing]
Mayra.
Where is she?
Over there.
[gentle heartfelt music playing]
[actress] She's so pretty.
She's so fair, isn't she?
Hi.
Hi. [chuckles]
[Alejandra (actress) chuckles]
[music fades]
Our deal is still on, right?
Yeah.
-You okay?
-I'm cold.
-I want to go to the bathroom.
-I'll give you my sweater.
One second.
There.
[baby cooing]
I'm going to pick her up.
[Mayra] That's fine.
[gentle heartfelt music resumes]
[actress] Hello.
[cooing]
You sweet baby.
Hey, baby girl.
[door closes]
-Shh, it's okay.
-[baby coos]
Shh.
How are you?
[groans faintly]
I'm fine.
Did they tell you
how much the baby weighed?
About two kilos.
So cute.
[Alejandra] I was holding her when
at around two or three in the afternoon…
[man] Hi. How are you?
[Alejandra] …this man shows up.
What are you doing here?
[tense music playing]
There's your little girl.
That's my daughter?
-Why is she holding her?
-He's the baby's dad?
-Yeah.
-[man] Let me see.
What's going on?
Mayra has a high fever.
[man] Well, go tell someone.
I'm not a doctor,
I don't know what's wrong.
Hey there, little one.
I'm going to get diapers for her.
[music stops]
[cell phone vibrates]
-Hi, love. Sorry.
-[Arturo] Why aren't you answering?
I've been calling you. Where are you?
Are they getting you ready to give birth?
No, I'm not giving birth yet.
Tell me what the doctors are saying.
Tell me what's going on.
Let me speak, Arturo.
What do you mean, what the doctors
are saying? I'm not dilated enough.
-They're seeing if it'll be a C-section.
-When are they doing the C-section?
I'm still at work. My boss hasn't told me
if I can leave early or not.
But I'll be there
as soon as I can. I'm coming.
No, it's not necessary
for you to come, Arturo. I'm okay.
I'm not able to talk right now
but I’ll keep you updated.
-Did he leave?
-[Mayra] He's gonna regret it.
I swear, that motherfucker's gonna pay.
He's gonna pay for this.
[fussing]
[actress] Okay. Okay. No. No.
Shh. Shh. Shh. Shh. Shh.
-Okay. Time to change the baby.
-[Mayra] I have to go.
I can't be here anymore.
-What do you mean? Where are you going?
-[quiet tense music playing]
Take the baby like we agreed.
My mom won’t let me back in the house.
I have to go to Chihuahua.
Look, Mayra, calm down.
The baby can't stay here alone.
We have to do things properly.
No, no, where are you going, Mayra.
Wait. No, just wait.
I already did everything I had to.
There’s the baby.
Isn't that’s what you wanted. Take her.
[Alejandra] I picked up the baby, went
into the hallway and turned around like,
"No, I can't."
"Even though I work
at the hospital and everything,
there's no way I can just leave
with the baby like this."
[ethereal music playing]
And that's when I thought,
"I better go, I'm leaving."
And I swear, I said,
"Enough, that's enough."
But I turned around and thought,
"If I leave the baby here,
what usually happens is,
because unfortunately,
babies are abandoned at hospitals,
if I leave the baby,
child services takes her."
"She doesn't deserve that."
"Just because I messed up?
But how am I gonna get her out?"
[baby fussing]
[suspenseful music playing]
-Ale, are you leaving?
-Yeah.
Get rest!
[cooing]
[man chatters]
[Alejandra] I left the hospital,
and that’s when… I don't know.
Maybe it was fate
or maybe it was just luck.
I don't know.
I was walking out and I heard someone say,
"What are you doing? Alejandra."
Alejandra! What happened?
[music stops]
What happened?
I already gave birth.
What are you thinking?
What happened? Why'd you leave?
Arturo, calm down, seriously.
Everything went well. The birth was fine.
What happened, Alejandra?
Tell me what happened.
I lost our child, okay?
-What?
-I lost our baby months ago.
What do you mean, you lost the baby?
How could…?
Look.
-They gave me this baby.
-[gasps] What? Are you serious?
-[gasping]
-Arturo! Arturo!
Listen to me. They gave her to me!
Arturo, they gave her to me.
-What'll I do with you? You're crazy.
-What do you mean?
-Get out and give them that baby.
-I'm not going!
-Take her back!
-I'm not taking her back!
-Take that baby back. Get out of the car!
-People don't give babies away! Get out.
Get the fuck out of here!
Arturo, please, listen to me. Arturo.
Arturo, just…
I am telling you, I am begging you.
The baby didn't do anything.
What will happen to her?
-Arturo, I’m talking to you! Listen to me!
-[anguished groaning]
Ah! Fine, get in!
EXIT
What are you gonna do?
Well…
It's just that Mayra,
the baby's mom, leaves early tomorrow.
I was going to pretend to be a family
member so they would let her go home.
And then, when you guys got there, I would
already have the baby and paperwork.
That's it, Arturo.
I didn't think this would happen.
-This just isn't right.
-Forgive me.
I love you, Arturo.
Please, please forgive me.
-Don't leave, my love.
-So that's why you lied then?
They couldn't find me out.
What would they say?
-Someone just gave her away.
-Why'd you keep me in the dark, Alejandra?
What are you getting me into, dammit?
I don't know. I don't know.
[baby fussing]
Shh. Shh.
-It's okay, it's okay.
-[gasps]
I don't care how you do it,
but I want my child, okay?
[baby coos]
-You're okay.
-[baby fusses]
Give her to me.
-It's okay.
-[fussing]
It's okay.
-[crying]
-No, no, don't be scared.
[quiet ethereal music playing]
[cooing]
It's okay, baby.
[kiss]
[music fades]
-[officer 1] Police!
-[officer 2] Police! Hands up!
-What happened?!
-[officer 1] Hands where I can see them!
-We didn't do anything!
-[officer shouting indistinctly]
[officer] Move it!
-No, no, no! Let go of me!
-Hey, calm down. Okay?
-We're going to get her checked out.
-I'm her mama!
-Arturo, my daughter! I'm her mama!
-Nothing's going to happen.
-[officer] Going to see if she's okay.
-[baby cries]
Ale, just do it! Just give her to 'em!
That's it, hand her over, slowly.
-[officer 2] We've got the girl back.
-Let her go!
-Let her go, you bastard! Let her go!
-[baby continues crying]
Stop hurting her, asshole!
[officer 2] Shut your mouth! You hear me?
-Identify yourself!
-Arturo Calderón Gamino!
And you? And you?!
[Arturo] She's Eleonor
Alejandra Marín Mendoza!
[officer 1] Eleonor
[moody music playing]
[chatter over police radio]
[radio host] We're playing songs
from the past.
For the romantics, we have this classic.
["Unchained Melody"
by The Righteous Brothers playing]
[Alejandra] We were in the squad car,
and that song started playing.
And the fact that we danced to it
on our wedding day,
that it was our special dance,
and to be hearing it then was like…
I don't know, like for me, I felt like
love is real and we were gonna be okay.
That's how I felt.
♪ And time ♪
♪ Goes by ♪
Sir, please, would you turn off that song?
Sir, please turn off that song!
Please, for the love of God, turn it off.
Please, just turn it off.
[gasps]
[moody whimsical music playing]
-[reporters] Ale!
-[overlapping shouting]
[reporter 1] Can we get a picture?
[overlapping chatter continues]
-[reporter 2] Did your husband help?
-[reporter 3] Plan everything together?
No, my husband had nothing
to do with this. And I'm not a thief.
I made arrangements
with the girl's mother.
Five months ago I saw her at the hospital.
We both talked at the clinic,
her and I, so…
She said she was a mother and single,
that it was her second child,
with a different father,
and that she wanted to abort it.
She told me she wanted
to get rid of it or give it away.
She assured me
she knew what she wanted to do with it,
so I asked to be considered.
[reporter 2] If you two had
an arrangement, why did you take the baby?
[reporter 4]
Arturo, were you part of the plan?
FEDERAL DISTRICT'S DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE
[news anchor 1]
They call her the baby snatcher.
Authorities believe she had help
from her husband, Arturo Calderón.
[news anchor 2]
…Mendoza and Arturo Calderón Gamino
the two suspects accused
of abducting a baby.
[news anchor 3] They stole the newborn
from Mexico General Hospital
while the parents were left
with overwhelming despair.
["En Otra Vida"
by Yami Safdie & Lasso playing]
[n Spanish] ♪ In another life ♪
♪ We got married
And traveled all over the world ♪
♪ We moved to a flat on the second floor ♪
♪ My parents
And your parents are friends ♪
♪ Our children ♪
♪ Have my patience and your smile ♪
♪ We go for strolls
And we read poetry ♪
♪ Shit, we had a great other life ♪
♪ Not this one ♪
♪ I don’t know why it didn’t work out ♪
♪ Maybe it was a whim of God ♪
♪ The courage
That they both always lacked ♪
♪ But I'll wait for you here ♪
♪ If you change your mind ♪
♪ It's not too late to return… ♪
I’ve served 13 years,
3 months and 25 days in prison.
When I first got here,
I was very hard for me.
Because not only was Alejandra
going to jail,
Alejandra was also being called a liar.
Alejandra had hurt her parents.
Alejandra had hurt her husband.
[distant shouting]
Alejandra had done the worst things
without meaning to.
The first few years were hard
because Arturo, my husband,
was considered my accomplice.
so I felt guilty about everything
that was happening to him.
I mean, I wanted to go through
what he was going through.
I wanted to…
If it was Arturo's turn
to use the bathroom at the men's prison,
I wanted to be in the bathroom with him.
And if he didn’t eat,
I didn't want to, stuff like that.
FEDERAL DISTRICT'S DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE
She did something unforgivable
in that moment.
And yeah, the feeling
is rage, pretty much.
That's the only thing that…
that I could feel toward her at the time.
I kept thinking, "Will this have
consequences, legally speaking,
or, like, kill my love for her?"
"Or should I just divorce Alejandra
because of this lie?"
[heartfelt music playing]
"Because she deceived me
because this is not my baby,
because she did things
she shouldn't have?"
"Or because she's not a good wife,"
and stuff like that.
"I'll never see her again."
That’s the only thing
I thought about while I was in jail.
Your head is about to explode.
I mean, the fear.
The terror,
it later becomes terror. It's just…
You want to cry and can't
because they will beat you up.
Or they'll beat you up even worse
because you're crying.
No, I mean, you're broken.
Emotionally, physically and in every way.
That's just part of the deal
when you go to jail.
-[contemplative music playing]
-[woman shouting]
[woman 1] Like that other shade.
I like this shade.
Here are the others.
I'll give you the other one later.
[woman 1] Go for a 4.1 or a 5.1
Oh, don't talk to Arturo,
baby, because you won't.
[Alejandra] Yesterday, when I called
Arturo, he was really intense.
[woman 2] I heard.
Oh, you were inside already?
-So you heard.
-[woman 2] What?
He got intense last night.
I called him and I'm like, "Hi, honey--"
[woman 2] He's going through andropause.
I said, "Hi, honey. How are you?"
And he says, "Hi. Fine, and you?"
And I say, "Fine, hon. What's up?"
"I'm mad."
[woman 2] Poor sweet thing.
[woman 1] His heart is aching.
You have to give in a little too.
You just want him to give in?
So what am I gonna do? Whatever he wants?
[woman 2] Beats me, girl.
Hurray for women's liberation.
-[all laugh]
-[Alejandra] Just that he always wins.
[woman 2] You won't…
You won't be able to control him anymore.
-No one values how hard he tries.
-Oh, no.
[news program music playing]
Pay attention, because this investigation
has two possible theories.
First, is that the girl was stolen.
Second hypothesis
is that she was given away.
But why?
At the time of her arrest,
this woman testified
that the baby was given away
by her birth mother.
Five months ago,
I met her at the hospital.
We were at the clinic when we had
our first conversation, her and I.
She tells me she was a single mother,
her second child with a different father,
and that she wanted an abortion.
She told me that she either wanted
to get rid of it or give away the baby.
REPORT OF SUSPICIOUS COUPLE
WITH A BABY
[news anchor] Eleonor is blaming
the newborn’s mother.
She said that they had made a deal
that she would give her the baby.
[Mayra] I felt guilty
for leaving her alone.
It was awful.
Desperation, anguish…
I wanted to hug her.
I hope she forgives me
for leaving her alone.
The justice system will be responsible
for shedding light on what happened
and, of course,
for punishing those responsible.
As a judge, you can’t, um…
dismiss a version of the facts
under the premise that,
"Oh, this is incredible,"
or "No, it’s impossible
that this happened."
"No, this doesn’t happen in real life."
Let's just say
that more things happen in real life
than fiction could ever envision.
So, it was possible.
It was possible that she had an agreement
with the girl's mother.
EVIDENCE
And we, the judges,
beyond the positions that people may have,
the truth is that everything is subject
to how it is proven,
or rather, whether it is proven
during the trial itself.
EVIDENCE
[Alejandra] The wedding veil,
what do you think?
[Arturo] The other thing
I want you to wear--
[judge] At the trial,
Alejandra told her story,
and she told it in a very consistent way.
regarding the suffering
that she had experienced.
A woman with a functional marriage,
but who does not feel satisfied
because she cannot fulfill the societal
expectation of being a mother.
["Unchained Melody" playing]
She is criticized by her husband's family,
in the sense that…
"Well, you are probably no good
as a woman if you aren't a mother."
The most a woman who cannot be a mother
can evoke in us is compassion.
In this story, as in many others,
we see how these gender roles
disproportionately affect women,
leading to tragic outcomes,
as happened in this case.
A family is the husband,
the mother, the house,
the car,
and the children.
And I think all of that began to cause
psychological damage to my daughter.
[gentle contemplative music playing]
When I said,
"I don't want to consider adopting,"
I want a child with my DNA,"
I maybe contributed
to closing myself off in that sense."
At some point, I did put pressure on her
because I said, "I wanna be a dad."
"I want to be a dad,
and I want to have a kid."
Obviously, being in jail, you have
a lot of time to think about things,
to see what
or where you failed as a partner.
At that time, I didn't understand it,
I didn't justify it, I didn't get it.
But I was starting to soften.
And with the problems I've told you about,
the ones I had in jail,
I started to talk more with Ale.
"Ale, I'm sorry
I didn't write to you before."
"I was confused and overwhelmed,
scared and depressed."
"For me, it's very difficult
to justify your lie."
"It causes me a lot of hurt and pain."
"Of course, what happened
was no small thing."
"But even so,
I forgive you with all my heart."
"Hello, my love, my beauty,
my light and my everything."
"I hope the bedbugs let you sleep,
you sleepyhead."
"Hey, my love, I wanted to tell you
something, I hope you don't mind."
"I’m going to work really hard
to save money and be able to do IVF."
"I read in the newspaper that we can
probably get a surrogate, my love,
and that we have
to get through this nightmare."
"You have to be strong."
"I love you with all my heart."
I spent two years in jail.
Two years and six months.
Until the trial was over.
And I was acquitted.
All the psychological damage
you get from being in jail,
they just tell you,
"Your sentence is acquitted."
"We'll destroy your record
right here in front of you."
"Look, you don't have a criminal record."
But the scar remains.
What we concluded in terms
of the theory of the crime,
is that there was no malicious intent
on his part.
He wasn’t an accomplice,
because he was only aware of Alejandra's
version of the encounter with Mayra.
And that alleged agreement with Mayra
was the weakest part
of Alejandra's defense.
The General Hospital
reported the disappearance,
and they made the request
to call the police.
When the police arrived,
they talked to her,
and that's when she said,
"Yes, she was stolen from me."
I'm guessing. As I said, I don't know.
But it wasn't until
the hospital reported it.
Obviously, I know that you can't do that,
so it had to be her or me in prison.
She couldn't have said,
"I gave away the baby,"
because that's illegal too, right?
[director] Mayra, it was hard
to get your version of the story.
For a long time,
I had only ever heard Ale’s version,
who told me that you met at the General
Hospital when you were pregnant,
and that on the day of the birth
you left the baby
and told her you were going to Chihuahua.
What do you think of this version?
Well, it's very illogical.
Super illogical, it's very…
I mean,
If you’re going to give away a baby,
you wouldn't do it
inside the hospital, right?
You wouldn't take her the way she did.
[moody dramatic music playing]
There was never a deal, never.
I'm telling you, I didn't see her
until the day Katya was born,
and the evidence shows that.
My pregnancy checkup records
are at the health center.
I only went to the hospital
to give birth, nothing else.
I had my pregnancy check-ups
at a health center.
I never set foot
in the hospital before that.
There is no way I could have met her.
PRENATAL CHECKUP
[judge] There were documents,
like Mayra's appointment card
where you could see
that her pregnancy checkups
were at a different clinic.
It wasn't until very late,
almost at the end of her pregnancy,
when she went to the General Hospital.
So, there was no correlation
between the circumstances
described by Alejandra
and the fact that, actually, Mayra had not
been physically at the hospital
until just a few weeks
before giving birth.
[intriguing music playing]
[Mayra] She was wandering around
the labor and delivery unit
and came to tell me
that she was doing a survey.
He showed me her ID,
her badge, and I trusted her.
She started asking a lot of questions.
She asked if it was my first daughter,
if this was from the same marriage,
and, well,
how was my relationship with the father.
I mean, she got everything from there.
Everything she told the police
was practically everything she asked me.
[director] Ale, what doesn’t fit
in your story is that the file says
you arrived at the hospital
posing as a social worker.
Were you conducting surveys?
[Alejandra] A lot of people
might say that, you know,
that I was doing surveys.
The truth is, it wasn't like that.
[director] You went to the maternity
ward saying you were a relative?
-[Alejandra] That she was my neighbor.
-I came to see a neighbor.
[Alejandra] Things like that.
That she was my neighbor,
and I had to go in to see her, and so on.
ELEONOR ALEJANDRA MARÍN MENDOZA
AREA 3 - UROLOGY
They found the sweater
Alejandra was wearing,
which had the badge
with her ID as hospital worker.
And they also found this folder
with the surveys,
which were the documents
Alejandra took with her
to start up a conversation.
I went into the hospital,
and Mayra was in bed.
I asked her, "How are you feeling?"
She said, "Really bad.
I have a high fever."
And then she said, "There's the baby."
And, well, I saw my daughter
for the first time, and
I fell in love with her.
-[Mayra] Vale.
-[father] Okay. My girl.
We're asleep.
For when she's older.
I'll have the video edited so she can see
where she was when she was born.
[in voiceover] At that point,
when I got there to meet my daughter,
Mayra was with someone.
I said, "Mayra, who is this?"
And Mayra said to me, "She’s a social
worker who's doing some surveys."
That's when she got up and left.
She got up,
left the papers and walked out.
Around 6:00 p.m. when visiting hours
were over, I went back to the room.
And she had already taken a shower.
And I said, "Is everything okay?"
And she said, "Yes, but he's gonna pay
for it, that motherfucker."
You know what?
Keep her, just like we agreed.
[actress] What do you mean?
[Alejandra] She said to me,
"I’m going to Chihuahua."
-I'm going to Chihuahua.
-[actress] You can't leave.
And I was like, "What?
What do you mean, you're leaving?"
I had a fever of almost 104 degrees.
They couldn't discharge me
because I had an infection.
They sent me for some urine tests.
I left the room and told my roommates,
I had two roommates,
"Keep an eye on my baby.
I'll be right back."
The bathroom was just
a few steps from the room.
-[suspenseful music playing]
-I came back, and my daughter was gone.
The first thing I thought was,
"Well, maybe they're bathing her,
-or they took her to feed her."
-[music stops]
I was sure a nurse had her.
Never, never did I think
my baby was kidnapped.
[intriguing music playing]
I was just told that my baby
was kidnapped from this hospital,
the General Hospital.
-I love my baby so much.
-[reporter 1] Talk to the public.
Please, help me get my baby back.
If you have her… [shuddering]
I'll give you my life,
everything I have,
but please, give her back to me, please.
[reporter 2] Is there anything else
you'd like to say?
[judge] This happened
in a public hospital.
OB-GYN EMERGENCIES
There is major institutional
accountability here.
The hospital security didn't work.
There was disregard
for Alejandra's situation,
having lost three babies
in the public health system.
There was no psychiatric intervention,
no one picked up
on what she was going through.
And on top of all of this,
Alejandra was actually
granted maternity leave
by a public health institution.
This was amazingly hard to believe.
And yet, it happened.
[mysterious music playing]
[Alejandra] The doctor measured me,
he checked me
and he weighed me.
-Good.
-[Alejandra] He heard the heartbeat.
I’ll grant you your maternity leave.
And honestly, you could hear it.
You could hear it.
Psychologists later told me,
in my court-mandated
psychological evaluation…
They explained to me that
oftentimes, your mind,
you suddenly strain your mind
into kind of echoing everything.
Which is what the doctor heard.
When two psychologists intervened,
they gave us an explanation
that clinically-speaking,
there are such things
as pseudo-pregnancies.
Her psychological pregnancy was a way
to mitigate the reality
of not having children.
It's a way, her reaction,
to all of the social demands
from her family.
So that's when the suggestion starts
and her psychological pregnancy begins.
And she says, "I started to gain weight."
"I started to feel nauseous."
"I started to feel pain in my hips."
She says, "My stomach started to grow."
-[Arturo] Sweetie.
-What?
-Our baby is coming tomorrow.
-Mm-hm.
[Arturo] Aren't you excited?
So much I can't even show it.
[Arturo] Let's see that big belly.
Before he's born, he can, when he sees
this video in about ten years,
he'll see how big
your belly was, the baby.
My baby is in there.
My son!
My beautiful baby.
Tomorrow, on Ishmael's Day,
but he'll be named Arturo
like his fucking father.
Everyone's going to come see him.
[judge] With the pressure
of having children
and Alejandra's history
of losing two prior pregnancies,
I understand that she believes this story.
And she also has the ability
to make everyone
around her believe it too.
[Arturo] He’s going to live here with us
in his house that we bought
just for him.
Right?
Evidence was presented that,
that I think
was conclusive in this regard.
There had been a baby shower.
They set up the monitor
and played the video
right there in the court.
It was shocking.
Because unless they
were all great actors and actresses,
it was conclusive proof
that Alejandra made her entire family
and other attendants believe
that she was pregnant.
[woman] Sofi, sit down, honey.
[overlapping chatter]
[people] Wow!
[woman] Bravo!
[all, in Spanish] Aw, how cute!
[woman] Ah, what could it be?
No, no, no. I didn’t guess,
it’s just a hunch.
They say you have to touch it.
[all, in Spanish] Rah-rah-boom, let’s go!
Boom-bam-rah-rah, hooray!
The baby, the baby! Rah, rah, rah!
Okay, does anyone want to say a few words
-or congratulate her?
-[woman] Me.
-[entertainer] María can do it, okay.
-Me, me.
-The mama.
-I, um, I want to thank you all.
You know, all her friends, after so many
years of knowing each other,
my sisters, my family.
Thank you all for coming
to celebrate with me,
because this baby has been long awaited.
-[woman] By the whole family.
-By this whole family.
And I hope everything goes well, my dear.
[woman] Everything will be fine.
-A beautiful baby girl.
-[people] Bravo!
[Alejandra's mother] I thought, "I'm gonna
have a grandchild from my daughter?"
But, when I saw the video,
I saw that sadness in her.
Immense sadness.
And that's why I think
she couldn't stop crying.
I said, "Hey,
you've gotta be happy, look,"
I hugged her and everything,
you know, because
it’s something we wanted.
-[child babbling]
-[moody mysterious music playing]
-[Alejandra's mom] How's it going?
-[Alejandra] What are you doing?
[Alejandra's mom] I'm here, my love,
getting ready to leave.
Ah, okay. And dad?
He's here.
What? What is Dad doing?
We were putting some things away.
Did you have breakfast?
Well…
I was chopping an onion and all that.
Uh-huh.
And I just made myself
a ham omelet with cheese.
Oh, good. I'm glad you had breakfast.
I made your dad some scrambled eggs.
[gentle upbeat music playing]
[people chattering in Spanish]
When you tell me to, I'll go over.
[woman] From the results
of the psychological evaluations,
the diagnosis we made of Alejandra
was that she tends to dissociate.
And, in that dissociation,
she convinces herself something is true
and is able to confuse fantasy
with reality.
And, if you add to that,
the pressure of wanting to be a mom,
it's what makes her misinterpret facts.
Because what she does wrong is,
she interprets everything in her favor.
[quiet mysterious music playing]
[judge] After the psychological evaluation
and the evidence submitted,
it wouldn't take much effort for anyone
to see how the story was coming together.
And, in the end,
the only thing that didn’t fit
was Mayra's alleged consent,
or the claims that she had consented.
[people shouting]
[Judge] With the history
of her psychological pregnancy,
all the social pressure,
we thought that Alejandra had acted
under the effect of this disorder,
and this had a significant impact
on how much punishment
she actually deserved.
Of course, other factors came into play,
and a very important factor
was that the baby girl was fine.
I opted for the minimum sentence.
I couldn't have imposed a lesser sentence,
because her behavior was very serious.
There was a victim, and in addition,
a father and a mother
who also wanted justice.
[Mayra] I don't have any sympathy for her.
I never have.
She didn't feel any sympathy
when she kidnapped my daughter.
And she hasn't shown any remorse either.
[gentle whimsical music playing]
If you ask me
if I have forgiven her or if I…
It's something that…
No, I couldn't do
and I don't think I can ever forgive her.
[judge] "This court finds
Eleonor Alejandra Marín Mendoza
criminally responsible
for the crime
of unlawful kidnapping of a minor
under 16 years old of age
with the intention
of harming her or someone else."
"It is therefore fitting
to impose a sentence
of 13 years and 4 months
in prison and a fine."
[music stops]
[woman] I don't know why you're here,
and I don't care.
But you suffered a lot.
It will be very hard for you.
But you will manage,
because your first card is triumph.
This is you.
In a good financial situation.
Here is your family.
With all your paperwork in order
and the marriage.
This is a good prison, a Kabbalistic
number seven, that you are in.
You haven't been in a bad prison.
Here is a card that is a bad card.
Maybe you will see it with your partner.
Maybe you will catch him cheating on you.
You will find something out,
because it's up here, infidelity.
Another question, my dear.
Should I stay with Arturo?
[woman] Here, the cards
are telling you to be alone for now.
To give yourself some space
and see which reality is best for you.
Here is Arturo.
And here is the woman,
the battle you are going to face.
Here, it shows loneliness,
but a lot of strength.
It is telling you an overwhelming victory
awaits you across the board,
with any man you want.
[crinkling noise]
[Alejandra] What did I do wrong
to be here?
Breaking the law.
Lying.
Deceiving.
Causing pain.
I was afraid and scared that
that he would leave me
for failing to become a mother
and that I'd be targeted and judged.
Actually, I was judged
for something much worse in the end.
-My love!
-Here's the ham.
How are you? Hm?
Soon you'll have
your dear wife back, my love.
Mmm.
What do you mean, "Mmm"?
You look so happy.
Why are you trying to hide it.
-I was saying--
-Everyone is making fun of me.
They're saying,
"Your bachelor days are over."
-Who's saying that?
-Everyone who, who goes to the store.
They're making fun of you
because the witch is coming back.
Yeah, they're like,
"You're gonna be whipped."
-"You won't be able to come here anymore."
-That's what they're saying?
Yeah.
No, but I do think
things are gonna change, right?
Yeah. One more weekend,
and then it's over.
After this weekend.
Wednesday, right?
I'm like, "Enough already.
Please, I'm done."
I'm very nervous.
Yes, the final stretch
is the hardest, right?
[melancholic music playing]
So, what,
everything's already finalized, right?
-No, honey, not really.
-What's up?
-I'm more nervous than before.
-What time are they letting you out?
-[Alejandra] I think around two.
-[music stops]
-I love you.
-You do?
I love you.
Oh, Ale, I’m going to miss you.
Done. Other hand.
So, are you guys gonna go to the beach?
Oh, Ale, this is so exciting.
-I want the river and the ocean.
-Oh yeah, you told me.
[Alejandra] You can swim
more easily in the river.
It's just harder in the ocean.
But I do want to go for a swim
in the ocean.
[gentle upbeat music playing]
-For you, my Carla.
-Thank you, sweetie.
-Wow, Carla.
-Thank you.
Someone can have these.
Oh, honey, your treasures.
My treasures.
You know they're my treasures. [chuckles]
Does anyone want a picture of my Arturo?
We can just drag this around. Look.
Jesus Christ.
And obviously,
you can take these two, honey.
Yes.
-I can’t leave you clothes, but, um…
-No, honey, I know.
This is enough. You’re leaving me
the most important thing.
[Alejandra] We’ll all gonna
be fine, you’ll see.
You'll see.
-You're the one forging this path.
-[Alejandra] Yes.
None of us have left yet,
but you're going to be first.
-[Alejandra] Yes.
-And you'll see.
-We'll start leaving one after another.
-[Alejandra] I'm opening the door for us.
-Yes, you are.
-[Alejandra] I’m taking you all with me.
Yes.
Don’t stop calling me
or picking up the phone.
I love you. I love you all so much.
-I love you. I love you so much.
-[Alejandra] I love you too, Carla.
[distant people shouting]
[Alejandra] During these
13 years in prison,
I have focused on accepting
not being a mom.
Before, I think my desire to be a mom
was more about pleasing others.
But what else is out there
beyond being a mom?
And finally understood
that there is so much to live for.
[women chattering]
You breathe just like that,
just like drinking water.
-She's so nervous.
-[guard] Wait one moment.
[Alejandra] I love you all so much.
[woman] A cheers for Ale.
[all] Hey!
One, two, three, Ale!
-[Alejandra] Thank you, loves.
-[woman] Love you.
[Alejandra] Thank you for everything.
-I don't want to leave you guys.
-[Carla] I'm really going to miss you.
-I love you very much.
-[Alejandra] Stay strong. Stay strong.
Strong.
[woman] I love you very much.
I love you all.
I'll never forget you, Ale.
I love you, girl.
Bye.
[Carla] Bye, Ale.
[chattering]
[gentle guitar music playing]
Oh, there she is!
[all cheering]
[Alejandra's mother] Oh, honey, come here.
We’re here.
We’re together again.
-[Alejandra] It’s over.
-[Alejandra's mother] It’s over, my child.
It's over.
[Arturo] Alejandra is leaving prison
at 39 years old. She went in at 26.
My love, I love you.
Bravo, Arturo!
[Arturo]
Of all the years we've been married,
I've lived alone longer than with her.
And she's not crying, right?
I’m happy with what I have
and what we can start over with.
Obviously, you always have
that nagging feeling
about having your own kids,
and if the opportunity arises to, well,
do IVF and get a surrogate,
yeah, maybe we will.
With a child, your last name,
and lineage, continues
and whatever you want them to carry on.
I would indeed like to have,
well, a child.
Not as much as before, but I still have
that desire engrained in me,
and I don't think it will ever go away.
[gentle guitar music continues]
[actress chuckles]
What do you think ours will be like?
As long as he doesn't turn out
like that one.
Is he moving?
Yeah, our baby just moved.
What's up, baby?
My baby son.
[Arturo chuckles]
[director] Cut!
What did you think?
It's…
[director] What about you?
[Arturo] Good, good.
Let's go.
[Arturo] Hey.
[Alejandra] Being a spectator
to my own story was very impactful.
In real life, I would've loved
to have been able to say,
"Take 1" or "Take 2,"
and be able to repeat scenes.
[director] I totally understand you, Ale.
And if we could write something
and think up some takes
or come up with a different ending
for this movie, what would you say?
If I could write the ending of this movie,
I think I would go
in a different direction.
I would keep growing.
And be able to enjoy myself.
And I would go…
I would go on a trip, I think.
To a beach
where I would be very happy and fulfilled.
[seagulls calling]
[director] Ale, I would've loved
your ending at the beach.
That would be a happy ending for me.
It's been two years
since you came out of prison,
and a lot has happened since you got out.
How would you finish the documentary?
What ending would I show?
Oh, my.
Life changes in the blink of an eye.
[heartfelt music playing]
When I got out of prison
Arturo told me again
that he still wanted to be a father.
And I told him that that was valid
and that he should go
and find his happiness.
That I definitely wasn't going
to undergo any treatment,
and that he wasn't going
to be a father with me.
We were separated for a while,
gave each other some space,
and he had another relationship,
a short affair
that resulted in his son being born.
Then, Arturo came looking for me.
We talked, and he told me
everything that had happened.
He told me that, well that
he missed me a lot, that he loved me,
and that he wanted me to be in his life.
That we should try again,
and I decided to give it a try.
It makes me very happy to see him smile
and to see him fulfilled as a father.
It makes me even happier
that he sees me in his life as,
as a mother or parent to his son.
Oh my goodness! Look at you!
Look how cute! Come here!
Run! Run! Run!
Come get me! Ah! Ah!
["En Otra Vida"
by Yami Safdie & Lasso playing]
Come here!
Ah! There he is!
I see you!
You can do it! You can do it!
Come on, my love, you can do it!
That's it! That's it!
Whoo!
Let's go eat. Shall we?
Do you want pizza?
["En Otra Vida" continues]
["En Otra Vida" ends]
[gentle melodic music playing]
[music becomes moody]
[music becomes ethereal]
[music fades]